Guide to the Andrew Ross Papers WAG.351
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Andrew Ross Papers
1994-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ross, Andrew
WAG.351
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 4 oversize folders
36.5 kilobytes in 18 documents
Andrew Ross (born 1956- ) is a scholar and social activist who teaches in the department of Social and Cultural Analysis at New York University (NYU). His papers consist of printed correspondence, personal notes, memorandum, reports, printed news articles, photographs, and other research documenting Andrew Ross's interest and involvement in the anti-sweatshop movement. Prominently featured materials pertain to Ross's correspondence and affiliation with organizations such as Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!), AFL-CIO, Worker Rights Consortium, NYU's local division in United Students Against Sweatshops (USAS) and the National Labor Committee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Andrew Ross in March 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.077.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Andrew Ross (1956- ) is a scholar and social activist who teaches in the department of Social and Cultural Analysis at New York University (NYU). He was born and educated in Scotland. As a scholar of social and cultural studies, his writings primarily focus on labor practices, organized labor, and urban sociology.
In the mid-to-late 1990s Ross was involved in the anti-sweatshop movement, which sought to prevent the use of clothing produced through the exploitation of underpaid workers in less economically privileged countries by wealthier countries. As the Director of the Graduate Program in American Studies at NYU Ross's research included working conditions in sweatshops in China, U.S. legislation on the prohibition of goods produced by sweatshops, and New York University's student-led No Sweat Coalition to prevent the selling of NYU apparel produced in sweatshops. In 1998 Ross published and edited No Sweat: Fashion, Free Trade, and the Rights of Garment Workers. He was also affiliated with the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!), Scholars, Artists, and Writers for Social Justice (SAWSJ), United Students Against Sweatshops (USAS) and the National Labor Committee, under which he was elected as one of its Directors in 1999. Additionally, Ross helped coordinate and organize events such as the United Students Against Sweatshops Conference in July 1999 and the Vigil to End Child Labor and Sweatshop Abuses held in New York City on December 9, 1999.
After the late 1990s, Ross became more involved in the academic labor movement, both as a member of the national, non-profit organization American Association of University Professors (AAUP), and as a strong supporter of NYU's graduate student union.
Scope and Contents
The Andrew Ross Papers (dated 1994-2000) consist of printed correspondence, personal notes, memorandum, reports, printed news articles, photographs, and other research documenting Andrew Ross's involvement in the anti-sweatshop movement of the mid-to-late 1990s. Prominently featured materials pertain to Ross's correspondence and affiliation with the organizations such as Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!), AFL-CIO, Workers Right Consortium, NYU's local division in United Students Against Sweatshops (USAS) and the National Labor Committee. Selected correspondence and notes illustrate Ross's participation in events such as the United Students Against Sweatshops Conference in July 1999 and the Vigil to End Child Labor and Sweatshop Abuses held in New York City on December 9, 1999. Additional newsletters, flyers, pamphlets, and booklets center on topics concerning workers' rights, labor practices in creating fashion wear, and campaigns against using clothing created in sweatshops.
A floppy disk included in the collection contains outlines and articles created in 1999 for a booklet produced by the Students Organizing for Labor and Economic Equality (SOLE). Articles focus on the history and mission of SOLE.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Sweatshops; Clothing workers; Child labor.; Anti-sweatshop movement; Labor unions; New York (N.Y.).; Labor; Ross, Andrew; New York University -- Employees
- National Labor Committee, 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1, 15)
- Harvard Trade Union Program: Summary and Report, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- AFL-CIO: Workers' Rights, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Labor: News Articles, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6-7, 16-19, 21)
- United Students Against Sweatshops, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Ross, Andrew: Correspondence, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10, 13-14)
- Workers' Rights Consortium, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Labor: Literature on Sweatshops, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ross, Andrew: Personal Notes, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ross, Andrew: Notes for Andrew Ross, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
- National Consumers League, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Fashion, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1, 16)
- Students Organizing for Labor and Economic Equality (SOLE) Booklet, 1999; TW_WAG_351_ER_1; 36.5 kilobytes in 18 documents (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_WAG_351_ER_1)
- Labor: Literature, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Ross, Andrew: Correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6, 10-11, 14)
- National Retail Federation, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Labor: News Articles, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8-9, 13, Box Shared Tamiment MSOS008)
- Fashion Industry Forum, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- American Apparel, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- National Labor Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 17, 19)
- Fashion Victims, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)